<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: emberjs | Balint Erdi]]></title>
  <link href="http://balinterdi.com/blog/categories/emberjs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://balinterdi.com/"/>
  <updated>2014-01-15T12:44:09+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://balinterdi.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Balint Erdi]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[How real-time updates work in Discourse]]></title>
    <link href="http://balinterdi.com/2014/01/14/how-real-time-updates-work-in-discourse.html"/>
    <updated>2014-01-14T11:06:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://balinterdi.com/2014/01/14/how-real-time-updates-work-in-discourse</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Given that I started engaging with web sites in the early 2000s there are still
some things today that I constantly marvel at. One of these things is real-live
update, the absolutely wonderful experience that I'm looking at a page and
it displays a change due to an action of another user right in front of my eyes,
without me hitting refresh.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.discourse.org/">Discourse</a>, being a state-of-the-art forum software does this, too,
and, provided my enthusiasm with all things that bring the web alive, I wanted to
understand how that works. More specifically I wanted to understand how
displaying new posts for the topic I am looking at can work its magic.</p>

<p>In the following post, I want to lead you through the whole process so that you
see exactly how the pieces fit together. In fact, that may be the thing I
enjoy most as a developer. Being able to take apart a complex application and
gain the comprehension of how the individual pieces function and how they are
orchestrated to make a complex system work.</p>

<h3>Tools</h3>

<p>Discourse is built on <a href="http://rubyonrails.org/">Ruby on Rails</a> and <a href="http://emberjs.com">Ember.js</a>, two fantasic
frameworks. Given my recent fascination with front-end development, and Ember.js
in particular, I'll focus on the front-end part here and only talk about the
back-end mechanism as much as it is needed to see the whole picture.</p>

<p><em>Consequently, some knowledge about Ember.js is assumed. You can go through the <a href="http://emberjs.com/guides/getting-ember/">Getting Started</a> guide on the official Ember.js site or -if you prefer
showing to telling- <a href="http://emberjs.balinterdi.com">sign up to my mailing list</a> to watch a series
of screencasts to get a basic grip on Ember.js architecture as we go through the
building of an application.</em></p>

<h3>Message bus</h3>

<p>Discourse uses a ruby gem (library) called <a href="message_bus">message_bus</a> that
enables listeners to subscribe to any channel of their liking and get notified
about events happening on that channel.</p>

<p>It also includes a <a href="https://github.com/SamSaffron/message_bus/blob/master/assets/message-bus.js">javascript lib</a> to allow connecting to the
message bus from the client-side application. That's what Discourse uses from
the Ember.js app. Let's see how.</p>

<h3>Subscribing to new posts on a topic</h3>

<p>When the user navigates to a topic page, the topic route gets activated and its
hooks run. After resolving the model, the <code>setupController</code> which, as its name
indicates, sets up the controller belonging to the model. It, among other
things, calls the subscribe method on the controller, see below:</p>

<p>``` js
Discourse.TopicRoute = Discourse.Route.extend({
  setupController: function(controller, model) {</p>

<pre><code>(...)
controller.subscribe();
(...)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
```</p>

<p>The controller for the model is Discourse.TopicController, so next we will look into
that:</p>

<p>``` js
Discourse.TopicController = Discourse.ObjectController.extend(..., {
  subscribe: function() {</p>

<pre><code>// Unsubscribe before subscribing again
this.unsubscribe();

var bus = Discourse.MessageBus;

var topicController = this;
bus.subscribe("/topic/" + (this.get('id')), function(data) {
  (...)

  // Add the new post into the stream
  topicController.get('postStream').triggerNewPostInStream(data.id);
});
</code></pre>

<p>  },
  (...)
}
```</p>

<p>The controller subscribes to the channel <code>/topic/&lt;topic_id&gt;</code>. The client polls
the message bus for potential new messages every 15 seconds. You can see the XHR
calls in the console of your browser:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/discourse-real-updates/xhr-polls.png" alt="Polling the message bus" /></p>

<p>When something is published to that channel, the callback function gets called
back with the data related to that event. The data, in that case, is going to be
the new post record. When the callback is fired, we call the
triggerNewPostInStream method on the postStream with the id of the post. What
does triggerNewPostInStream do, then? We can check that in the PostStream model.</p>

<p>``` js
/<strong>
  We use this class to keep on top of streaming and filtering posts within a topic.
</strong>/
Discourse.PostStream = Em.Object.extend({
  (...)
  /**</p>

<pre><code>Finds and adds a post to the stream by id. Typically this would happen if we receive a message
from the message bus indicating there's a new post. We'll only insert it if we currently
have no filters.
</code></pre>

<p>  **/
  triggerNewPostInStream: function(postId) {</p>

<pre><code>(...)

var loadedAllPosts = this.get('loadedAllPosts');

if (this.get('stream').indexOf(postId) === -1) {
  this.get('stream').addObject(postId);
  if (loadedAllPosts) { this.appendMore(); }
}
</code></pre>

<p>  },
}
```</p>

<p>The docstring is quite revealing. If the post id is already in the stream, we
don't do anything. If it is not, we add it to the stream (an Ember array). If
the loading of posts has finished, we are ready to append the new posts to the
stream.</p>

<p>Notice we are adding post <em>ids</em>, not actual post records so the next
investigation step is to explore how ids get turned into records.</p>

<p>``` js
/**
  Appends the next window of posts to the stream. Call it when scrolling downwards.</p>

<p>  @method appendMore
  @returns {Ember.Deferred} a promise that's resolved when the posts have been added.
**/
appendMore: function() {
  var self = this;</p>

<p>  // Make sure we can append more posts
  if (!self.get('canAppendMore')) { return Ember.RSVP.resolve(); }</p>

<p>  var postIds = self.get('nextWindow');
  if (Ember.isEmpty(postIds)) { return Ember.RSVP.resolve(); }</p>

<p>  self.set('loadingBelow', true);</p>

<p>  var stopLoading = function() {</p>

<pre><code>self.set('loadingBelow', false);
</code></pre>

<p>  };</p>

<p>  return self.findPostsByIds(postIds).then(function(posts) {</p>

<pre><code>posts.forEach(function(p) {
  self.appendPost(p);
});
stopLoading();
</code></pre>

<p>  }, stopLoading);
},
<code>``
The above</code>appendMore` method is responsible for retrieving the post ids that
have to be added below the currently visible posts and turning these ids into
actual post records.</p>

<p>We are getting close now, but let me speed things up a bit by only explaining the
process but not showing all the code which makes it so that the new post objects
are finally pushed to the <code>posts</code> array from where they will be finally
displayed. (If you are such a code untangler as I am, and would like to see the
code, it is <a href="https://github.com/discourse/discourse/blob/0fd193fac314610d7a93d7b4af84a4bc1e52d03e/app/assets/javascripts/discourse/models/post_stream.js">right here</a>)</p>

<p>What happens is that the new posts get displayed in windows, not one by one.
This window is kept updated in the <code>nextWindow</code> property, from the stream we
pushed post ids into.  It is the slice in this stream that starts at the last
loaded post id and has a maximum length of <code>posts_per_page</code>, a configuration
setting.  This construct also makes it possible, quite ingeniously, for this
same code to load the next batch of posts to the page as the user scrolls down.</p>

<p>The window still contains ids and to fetch the related post records an identity
map (yes, Discourse has its <a href="http://balinterdi.com/2013/12/03/roll-your-own-ember-dot-js-identity-map.html">identity map implementation</a>,
too!) is used via the <code>findPostsByIds</code> method. Once the records are retrieved ,
they are each passed to the <code>appendPost</code> method that just pushes them to the
<code>posts</code> array.</p>

<h3>Displaying the new post in the topic stream</h3>

<p>The only thing remains to be seen for the whole picture to be clear is how the
stream of posts is displayed in the browser. The template that renders the
topic, along with its posts, is <a href="https://github.com/discourse/discourse/blob/0fd193fac314610d7a93d7b4af84a4bc1e52d03e/app/assets/javascripts/discourse/templates/topic.js.handlebars">the topic template</a>.</p>

<p>The relevant part of the template is below:</p>

<p><div><script src='https://gist.github.com/8434790.js'></script>
<noscript><pre><code>&lt;html&gt;&lt;body&gt;You are being &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/gist/8434790&quot;&gt;redirected&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/body&gt;&lt;/html&gt;</code></pre></noscript></div>
</p>

<p>If the post stream is not loading, we render the posts through the cloaked
collection. I will not go into details about what
<a href="https://github.com/eviltrout/ember-cloaking">cloaked-collection</a> does, (but I highly recommend <a href="http://eviltrout.com/2014/01/04/hiding-offscreen-ember.html">a blog
 post on it by its author, @eviltrout</a>), the important thing in the
current discussion is that it renders the <code>post</code> template (cloakView="post") for
each post from <code>postStream.posts</code> (content=postStream.posts).</p>

<p>That is where the two parts come together. Since a binding is established with
the above handlebars line to the posts property of the postStream, every time
new posts are added (see how in the first part of the walkthrough), the
collection is going to be rerendered and consequently the posts appear in
"real-time". The magic of Ember.js bindings.</p>

<h3>In parting</h3>

<p>I skipped over a couple of things so that this post does not turn into a
chapter of a novel, but I hope that my walkthrough could let you peek behind
the curtains and see how such a miraculous feature is made possible.</p>

<p>The key takeaway is that building with the right tools (namely the message bus and
the solid foundations of Ember.js), which a lot of people have put an enormous
amount of time into, makes such a killer feature within your reach. Not easy,
but definitely doable.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[At Your Service: Publicly Available API for the Rock and Roll Ember.js App]]></title>
    <link href="http://balinterdi.com/2013/12/31/at-your-service-publicly-available-api-for-the-rock-and-roll-emberjs-app.html"/>
    <updated>2013-12-31T09:38:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://balinterdi.com/2013/12/31/at-your-service-publicly-available-api-for-the-rock-and-roll-emberjs-app</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>So far, if you wanted to code along <a href="http://emberjs.balinterdi.com">my developing an example Ember.js
application</a>, Rock &amp; Roll, you had to run the server side
component. That required ruby to be installed on your machine, and you had to
<a href="https://github.com/balinterdi/rock-and-roll-api">clone the repository</a>, and start the server each time you wanted to
make some progress with the application.</p>

<p>I realized that might be cumbersome and thus I made the server publicly
available at <a href="http://rock-and-roll-api.herokuapp.com/">http://rock-and-roll-api.herokuapp.com</a>.</p>

<p>I have also updated <a href="https://github.com/balinterdi/rock-and-roll/commit/remote-api">the client-side component to connect to that remote
api.</a>. All backend requests now go through App.Adapter.ajax which
basically just delegates to <code>Ember.$.ajax</code> prefixing urls with the backend host:</p>

<p>``` javascript
App.Adapter = {
  ajax: function(path, options) {</p>

<pre><code>return Ember.$.ajax('http://rock-and-roll-api.herokuapp.com' + path, options)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<p>If you work with an earlier version of the client app, you might have to
rewrite urls in multiple places but I figured it is still less work than running
the server yourself.</p>

<p>I hope that facilitates your working along with the Rock &amp; Roll app and makes
your journey to Ember.js proficiency smoother. If you want to see the
screencast series in which I develop said application, you can <a href="http://emberjs.balinterdi.com">sign up to my
mailing list</a> and have each episode auto-delivered to your inbox.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
