<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ember.js | Balint Erdi's blog about Ember.js]]></title>
  <link href="http://balinterdi.com/blog/categories/ember-js/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://balinterdi.com/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-03T15:23:20+02:00</updated>
  <id>http://balinterdi.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[I'm all about Ember.js recently]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Rock and Roll with Ember.js v1.13 is out]]></title>
    <link href="http://balinterdi.com/2015/07/03/rock-and-roll-with-ember-dot-js-v1-dot-13-is-out.html"/>
    <updated>2015-07-03T15:25:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://balinterdi.com/2015/07/03/rock-and-roll-with-ember-dot-js-v1-dot-13-is-out</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today marks the sixth release of my book, <a href="http://rockandrollwithemberjs.com">Rock and Roll with Ember.js</a>, and
brings it in sync with Ember 1.13. The book follows along the development from
scratch of an Ember application, and chapter by chapter and explains concepts in
the process.</p>

<p>As I have promised, the book is kept up-to-date with the latest stable Ember
version. That implies both using idiomatic Ember and not using deprecated
syntaxes or APIs.</p>

<p>Now that the versioning of Ember Data is in lockstep with that of Ember, I
considered it important to update to the latest Ember Data, too, and will
strive to do so in future releases, too.</p>

<p>Here are the major things I updated for the 1.13 release:</p>

<ul>
<li>Use <code>this.route</code> instead of <code>this.resource</code> in the router map as the latter is now deprecated.</li>
<li>Use <code>Ember.computed</code> and <code>Ember.on</code> instead of the Function prototype
extensions, <code>property</code> and <code>on</code> as extending the Function prototype is
consired a poor practice.</li>
<li>Update the "Getting ready for Ember 2.0" chapter as most things are clear now
for the 2.0 release. As I give particular examples for each deprecation, this
chapter can also serve as an update guide for 1.x Ember applications.</li>
<li>Use the new Ember Data find methods, namely <code>store.findAll</code> and
<code>store.findRecord</code>. Before, both fetching a collection and a single record
used <code>store.find</code>.</li>
</ul>


<p>As usual, there are also smaller improvements and fixes and you can find the
whole list in the errata/issues repository for the book, assigned to <a href="https://github.com/balinterdi/rarwe-issues/issues?q=milestone%3A1.13+is%3Aclosed">the release milestone.</a></p>

<p>If you don't yet have the book, you can <a href="http://rockandrollwithemberjs.com/#signup">download a sample chapter</a> and see if you like it.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Common Ember Mistakes]]></title>
    <link href="http://balinterdi.com/2015/06/05/common-ember-mistakes.html"/>
    <updated>2015-06-05T00:27:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://balinterdi.com/2015/06/05/common-ember-mistakes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I wrote an article called <a href="http://www.toptal.com/emberjs/the-8-most-common-ember-js-developer-mistakes">"The Top 8 Most Common Ember.js Developer
Mistakes"</a> for Toptal that just went live on their blog. As the name
suggests, it describes the typical pitfalls beginner, and sometimes advanced,
Ember developers make with a mitigation strategy for each of them. I am quite
happy about how it turned out and suggest you <a href="http://www.toptal.com/emberjs/the-8-most-common-ember-js-developer-mistakes">give it a read</a>.</p>

<p>Also, it turned out to have more than 2500 words so I thought it might be
convenient for you to have it as a pdf. It spans 13 pages and you can get it
right here below:</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[My book, Rock and Roll with Ember.js, is now live!]]></title>
    <link href="http://balinterdi.com/2015/02/18/rock-and-roll-with-ember-js-is-live.html"/>
    <updated>2015-02-18T09:51:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://balinterdi.com/2015/02/18/rock-and-roll-with-ember-js-is-live</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I started writing my book, Rock &amp; Roll with Ember.js, on July 18, 2014, exactly
7 months ago (More precisely, I prepared some drafts from early chapters most of
which I ended up rewriting before that, but who doesn't like a good story?).</p>

<p>Today, I am extremely happy to announce that <a href="http://rockandrollwithemberjs.com">the book is available for purchase</a>!</p>

<h2>Tame the dreaded Ember.js learning curve</h2>

<p>Ember is said to be hard to learn. Developers who are new to the framework hit
a wall and can't easily find out how all the pieces fit together.</p>

<p>My own experience tells me that Ember has a small number of core concepts that
you have to grok to be able to tame the learning curve. Once you understand
these key ideas behind the framework's design, you will fly over that wall and
see the green meadow filled with flowers and bunnies.</p>

<p>You will build Ember applications with confidence and - if you are like me -
you will love building them.</p>

<h2>Read it and build it!</h2>

<p>My book also has a concept, and a very pragmatic one at that.</p>

<p>In the book, we are building an application, chapter by chapter. As we
progress, we are adding new features to the application, introducing new
Ember concepts that are needed for implementing the feature.</p>

<p>When a list of bands need to be displayed alongside with the songs of the
selected band, we reach for nested routes.  When we need a widget that displays
stars for the songs, we introduce components. When we want to show the user
that loading data from the backend is in progress, we learn about loading
routes.</p>

<h2>Set List</h2>

<p>The book currently has the following chapters:</p>

<ol>
<li>Introduction to Ember.js</li>
<li>Ember CLI</li>
<li>Templates and data bindings</li>
<li>Routing</li>
<li>Nested routes</li>
<li>Actions</li>
<li>Components</li>
<li>Controllers</li>
<li>Advanced routing</li>
<li>Talking to a backend - with Ember Data</li>
<li>Testing</li>
<li>Sorting and searching with query params</li>
<li>Loading and error routes</li>
<li>Helpers</li>
<li>Getting ready for Ember 2.0</li>
</ol>


<p>I say 'currently' because I will definitely have to change some chapters as
Ember evolves (To give an example, Controllers will probably become Routable components).</p>

<h2>A reference book and a reference application</h2>

<p>Ember moves rapidly towards version 2.0. As each minor version is released, it
brings new syntaxes and deprecates old ones. Even though the Ember Core team
takes extreme care to ensure a smooth upgrade process, it is easy for an
application to lag behind, having a few deprecations here and there and not
using the shiny new tools.</p>

<p>The motto of the Ember 2.0 roadmap is "Stability without Stagnation", that old
syntaxes and practices should vanish gradually, giving ample time for developers
to update their applications. At the same time, Ember should not stagnate, it
should introduce new features.</p>

<p>I adhere to this motto, but, more importantly, my book does, too.</p>

<p>I want the book and the Rock &amp; Roll application to be up-to-date with the latest
stable Ember version and not have any of the deprecations. What that means in
practice is that if you buy one of the packages, you will most likely get book
updates after each 1.x release. And at no extra cost to you until 2.0 ships!</p>

<h2>A bonus deal you will definitely like</h2>

<p>When you <a href="http://rockandrollwithemberjs.com/#stairway-to-heaven">buy one of the packages</a> you also get access to an awesome deal
from <a href="https://divshot.com">Divshot</a>, a company that provides static hosting for your Ember apps.</p>

<p>You get 3 months free of <a href="https://divshot.com/pricing">their Fleet plan</a>, a $150 value.</p>

<h2>The "New Beginning" tour</h2>

<p><del>Wait, there is more!</del> To celebrate that the book has finally seen the
light of day, there is a 25% discount <a href="http://rockandrollwithemberjs.com/#pricing">on all packages</a>.</p>

<p>This offer expires on Sunday, February 22, at 23:59 PST, so <a href="http://rockandrollwithemberjs.com">grab yours</a> now!</p>

<h2>Acknowledgements</h2>

<p>I am indebted to all of you who have pushed me through the finish line, either
by praising my screencasts, blog posts and review copies of my book, retweeting
my marketing tweets, giving valuable feedback that made the book better or
simply by pointing out typos in the text.</p>

<p>I would also like to thank you to the Ember Core team whose relentless work
makes Ember better every day. You are putting so much time in, it's almost
insane. It's kinda obvious but without your contributions, this book would not
exist.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Reminiscing about EmberFest 2014]]></title>
    <link href="http://balinterdi.com/2014/09/05/reminiscing-about-emberfest-2014.html"/>
    <updated>2014-09-05T09:55:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://balinterdi.com/2014/09/05/reminiscing-about-emberfest-2014</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://emberfest.eu">EmberFest 2014</a> ended a week ago and I already feel nostalgic. It
was a great event with great people and you could feel the excitement about
Ember in the air and in all conversations. It was almost single-handedly
organized by <a href="https://haagen-software.no">Joachim Haagen-Skeie</a> for which he deserves huge kudos.</p>

<p>It was really great to associate real people with twitter avatars and have
fascinating conversations about various topics that included the Ember
Inspector, the difficulties in building a build tool and even Firefox OS.</p>

<h3>The functional paradigm making a headway into Emberland</h3>

<p>One thing that struck me about Ember initially is that it seems to rely heavily
on (shared) state. Some (most?) of that is inevitable given Ember being a
performant framework that runs in the browser and is written in Javascript.
None of these facilitates ditching (or minimizing) state and go with a
functional, stateless approach.</p>

<p>On the other hand, I really came to cherish the <a href="http://www.infoq.com/presentations/Simple-Made-Easy">simplicity</a> of the
functional paradigm and have been gravitating towards languages that allow this
(Clojure was, and still is, <a href="http://balinterdi.com/2013/06/19/the-appeal-of-one-paradigm-languages.html">my favorite</a>). So I added a mental
note about my two favorite things being at such a great distance from each other
and moved on.</p>

<p>One theme of the conference and the hallway talks, however, is how Ember
embraces the functional, immutable approach where it makes sense to. It might
have something to do with my confirmation bias, but let me cite the examples
nevertheless. <a href="https://twitter.com/tchak13">Paul Chavard</a> had a talk on his using immutable data
structures in Ember. <a href="http://www.solitr.com/blog/">Jo Liss</a> revealed how Broccoli uses a
"rebuild-from-scratch" approach instead of trying to find out which assets to
rebuild at each modification. Finally, Alex Matchneer, aka. machty, prolific
Ember and router.js contributor had <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1afMLTCpRxhJpurQ97VBHCZkLbR1TEsRnd3yyxuSQ5YY/edit#slide=id.p">a presentation on React vs.  Ember</a>
at EmberNYC which you should go read. His <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1afMLTCpRxhJpurQ97VBHCZkLbR1TEsRnd3yyxuSQ5YY/edit#slide=id.g380053cce_1786">last slide</a> has a bullet-point
that states: "Don't be surprised if Ember adopts DOM-diffing".</p>

<p>It would be an understatement if I said I'm happy to see the functional world
coming to Ember.</p>

<h3>Promises</h3>

<p>I had a talk at the conference called "Don't call me back - How Ember uses
promises and how you can, too". As it usually happens, in doing research for the
talk, I learned a lot not just about promises but about other topics, too. This
time, it was the (in)famous run loop I stumbled across on several
occasions so I am really happy I know a lot more about that beast now. You can
find the slides of my presentation below.</p>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-slide="10"
data-id="47ee01e011b60132c86e02e2e0c65448" data-ratio="1.33333333333333"
src="http://balinterdi.com//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<p>I might even do another talk "How Ember uses the run loop and how you should
probably not", or something to this effect.</p>

<h3>EmberFest 2015</h3>

<p>The greatest thing about EmberFest was its vibe. I saw the tweets coming
in from EmberConf this March and <a href="http://reefpoints.dockyard.com/2014/03/17/emberconf-picks-ups-where-the-rails-community-left-off.html">the post-conf blog posts</a>
about the awesome community and how one could feel the excitement that we are
building apps with a tool that is new and hot now but is probably going to be
the framework of choice for many in a few years. It is definitely a fascinating
world to live in.</p>

<p>I'll certainly be there at EmberFest 2015, so hopefully see you there!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Ember gotcha: Controllers are singletons]]></title>
    <link href="http://balinterdi.com/2014/06/26/ember-gotcha-controllers-are-singletons.html"/>
    <updated>2014-06-26T08:25:00+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://balinterdi.com/2014/06/26/ember-gotcha-controllers-are-singletons</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is a somewhat subtle bug in the current version of the Rock &amp; Roll with
Ember app. If you start to create a song for an artist that does not have one
and then switch to another one, the song creation process does not need to be
restarted by clicking on the "Why don't you create one?" link. Also, if you've
already partially inputted the name of the song for the first one, it stays
there for the second artist:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/singleton-controllers/start-song-creation-for-radiohead.png" alt="Start creating a song for Radiohead" />
<img src="/images/posts/singleton-controllers/new-song-for-radiohead.png" alt="Input Karma for Radiohead" />
<img src="/images/posts/singleton-controllers/new-song-for-rhcp.png" alt="Observe song title stays for Red Hot Chili Peppers" /></p>

<p>The above behavior was brought to my attention by <a href="https://twitter.com/davidlormor">David</a>
<a href="http://davidlormor.com">Lormor</a>, an astute reader and watcher of my screencasts.</p>

<p>In some circumstances it is desirable for the result of some user interaction to
linger between route transitions but in other cases it is not. I put the
current example firmly in the latter camp and thus consider the above a bug.</p>

<p>Let me explain what causes this behavior and then provide a simple solution to fix it.</p>

<h3>Repeat after me: controllers are singletons</h3>

<p>Controllers in Ember are singletons. Controllers in Ember are singletons.
Controllers in Ember are singletons.</p>

<p>When the user leaves a page and goes to another one, the controller is not
torn down. It lives on, keeping its properties.</p>

<p>This makes total sense for a framework that aims to be a tool for creating
long-lived, rich-client side applications but is something to watch out for
when you develop Ember applications.</p>

<p>If you have a long background in back-end development, like yours truly,
it is especially easy to fall prey to this, as you could see.</p>

<h3>Same controller, different model</h3>

<p>Initially, when the applicaiton is loaded, the <code>songCreationStarted</code> property
of the controller is set to false. When the user clicks the "create one" in the
"Why don't you create one?" blurb, it is set to true and thus the text input
field appears to allow adding a new song.</p>

<p>Now comes the tricky part. If the user then decides to go to a different artist,
she clicks the name of another artist in the sidebar. What happens? A transition
is made from one <code>ArtistSongsRoute</code> to another <code>ArtistSongsRoute</code>. The artist
is going to be different but the same <code>ArtistSongsController</code> is used.</p>

<p>To prove my point, here are two screenshots of the Ember Inspector's sidebar.
The first one is before, the second one is after the transition between
<code>/artists/radiohead/songs</code> and <code>/artists/red-hot-chili-peppers/songs</code>:</p>

<p><img src="/images/posts/singleton-controllers/ember-inspector-radiohead-songs.png" alt="Ember Inspector - Radiohead songs" />
<img src="/images/posts/singleton-controllers/ember-inspector-rhcp-songs.png" alt="Ember Inspector - RHCP songs" /></p>

<p>You can see that the controller is the same Ember object but the value of the <code>artist</code> property changes.</p>

<h3>Understanding the problem</h3>

<p>When the transition is made between the two artists, the artist object is
changed and consequently any data bound to the artist (and the <code>artist</code> property
of the <code>ArtistSongs</code> controller) is going to be rerendered but, since the
controller instance is not changed, unrelated data will stay unchanged on
screen.</p>

<p>What happens in the code? If you take a look at the template, you see that the
text input field is shown if <code>canCreateSong</code> is true:</p>

<p><div>
  <pre><code class='html'>&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;text/x-handlebars&quot; data-template-name=&quot;artist/songs&quot;&gt;
  {{#if canCreateSong}}
    &lt;div class=&quot;list-group-item&quot;&gt;
      {{input type=&quot;text&quot; class=&quot;new-artist&quot; placeholder=newSongPlaceholder value=newTitle insert-newline=&quot;createSong&quot; }}
      &lt;button class=&quot;btn btn-primary btn-sm new-song-button&quot; {{action &quot;createSong&quot;}}&gt;Add&lt;/button&gt;
      (...)
    &lt;/div&gt;
  {{/if}}
&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;</code></pre>
</div>
</p>

<p><code>canCreateSong</code> is defined in the controller and is true if either
<code>songCreationStarted</code> is true or if there are already songs. Since
<code>songCreationStarted</code> has just been set to true by the <code>enabledSongCreation</code>
action (and the controller instance is not changed) when the user clicked the
"create one" link for the first artist, <code>canCreateSong</code> stays true and the
text field stays visible:</p>

<p>```js
App.ArtistSongsController = Ember.ArrayController.extend({
  (...)
  songCreationStarted: false,
  canCreateSong: function() {</p>

<pre><code>return this.get('songCreationStarted') || this.get('length');
</code></pre>

<p>  }.property('songCreationStarted', 'length'),</p>

<p>  actions: {</p>

<pre><code>enableSongCreation: function() {
  this.set('songCreationStarted', true);
}
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  (...)
});
```</p>

<h3>A simple fix</h3>

<p>To fix this, the simplest solution is to manually reset the properties that we
do not want to persist.</p>

<p>One solution is to do this in the <code>setupController</code> of the route since that
always gets called when transitioning to a new route:</p>

<p>```js
App.ArtistSongsRoute = Ember.Route.extend({
  (...)
  setupController: function(controller, model) {</p>

<pre><code>this._super(controller, model);
controller.set('artist', this.modelFor('artist'));
controller.set('newTitle', '');
controller.set('songCreationStarted', false);
</code></pre>

<p>  },
  (...)
});
```</p>

<p>And that totally works. However, I prefer placing this "resetting" code in the
controller, probably because it is strictly controller-related and also because
I can make the code really telling there:</p>

<p>```js
App.ArtistSongsController = Ember.ArrayController.extend({
  (...)
  songCreationStarted: false,
  canCreateSong: function() {</p>

<pre><code>return this.get('songCreationStarted') || this.get('length');
</code></pre>

<p>  }.property('songCreationStarted', 'length'),</p>

<p>  artistDidChange: function() {</p>

<pre><code>this.set('newTitle', '');
this.set('songCreationStarted', false);
</code></pre>

<p>  }.observes('artist'),
  (...)
});
```</p>

<p>The <code>observes</code> function property extension will run the <code>artistDidChange</code> code
every time the <code>artist</code> property of the controller changes and that is exactly
when we need to clear the title and allow the song creation process to be
restarted. Nice, clean and does exactly one thing.</p>

<p><em>Note: The latest version of the code that contains these changes is <a href="https://github.com/balinterdi/rock-and-roll/releases/tag/fix-start-song-creation-bug">available on Github</a>.</em></p>

<h3>Model Dependent State - UPDATE</h3>

<p>It turns out I stumbled into something substantial. As <a href="http://localhost:4000/2014/06/26/ember-gotcha-controllers-are-singletons.html#comment-1461013970">Luke Melia points out</a> below in the comments (thank you, Luke!),
the above problem has been under consideration for a while.</p>

<p>Alex Matchneer, a member of the Ember core team gave <a href="http://youtu.be/Syv_OTzHOr0">a presentation at EmberConf</a> in which he explains that there is a missing
primitive.</p>

<p>He calls it "Model Dependent State" and it is what would decide under what
conditions a certain controller property is "sticky" (whether it retains its
value when you change the model of a certain controller or not).</p>

<p><a href="http://youtu.be/Syv_OTzHOr0?t=14m18s">Here</a> is the part where he begins to talk about Model
Dependent State.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
